كفر دلة فوقاني قرية سورية جميلة تقع غرب مدينة عفرين
Kafr Dalleh Fawqani is a beautiful Syrian village located
west of Afrin.
في ريف حلب الشمالي بـ 15 كيلومتراً وتتبع لها.
It is located 15 kilometers away in the northern countryside
of Aleppo, and is affiliated with it.
كما أنها تقع إلى الشرق من مدينة جنديرس بـ 15 كيلومتراً.
It is also located 15 kilometers east of the city of
Jindires.
وإلى الشمال الغربي من مدينة حلب بـ 75 كيلومتراً.
And 75 kilometers northwest of the city of Aleppo.
إلى الشمال منها تقع قرية تل غازي.
To its north lies the village of Tal Ghazi.
أما جنوبها فتقع قرية كفر دلة تحتاني.
While to its south lies the village of Kafr Dalleh Tahtani.
وغربها قرية صاطيا وسلسلة جبلية، أما شرقها فتقع قرية معراتة.
To its west is the village of Satya and a mountain range,
while to its east lies the village of Ma'arata.
تقع على أطراف ثلاثة أودية: وادي الجب، ووادي الصخور، ووادي
السفينة.
It is located on the edges of three valleys: Al-Jubb Valley,
Al-Sukhour Valley, and Al-Safina Valley.
وتشرف عليها من جهاتها الأربع هضاب جبلية كلسية.
It is overlooked from all four sides by calcareous mountain
plateaus.
وكفر دلة فوقاني من أقدم القرى الموجودة في المنطقة.
Kafr Dalleh Fawqani is one of the oldest villages in the
area.
وقد كان سكانها الأوائل يربون الأغنام، وجاؤوا إلى المنطقة
بحثاً عن الماء والكلأ.
Its early inhabitants used to raise sheep, and they came to
the area in search of water and pasture.
وسكنوا بداية في المغاور والكهوف الموجودة في المنطقة.
They initially lived in the caves and caverns found in the
region.
وفيها بئر ماء قديم كان له أهمية حيوية كبيرة في تاريخ القرية.
It has an old water well that had great vital importance in
the history of the village.
والقرى المجاورة لها التي شربت من هذا البئر.
And for its neighboring villages that drank from this well.
تبلغ مساحة القرية 300 هكتار، مزروعة بأشجار الزيتون والمشمش
والرمان.
The village's area is 300 hectares, planted with olive
trees, apricots, and pomegranates.
والمحاصيل الزراعية البعلية.
And rain-fed agricultural crops.
وقد أُنشئت أول مدرسة من قبل أهالي القرية في عام 1947.
The first school was established by the village residents in
1947.
بجهود الأستاذ حيدر كنجو، الشخصية المثقفة المعروفة في كامل
قضاء عفرين.
Through the efforts of Mr. Haidar Kanjo, the well-known
educated figure in the entire Afrin district.
والذي له باع ومساهمة كبيرة في إنشاء القرية وفي نشر التعليم
في المنطقة.
Who had a significant role and contribution in establishing
the village and spreading education in the region.
أهالي القرية يحبون الموسيقى والحفاظ على الفلكلور والتراث
الغنائي في المنطقة.
The villagers love music and preserving the folklore and
musical heritage in the region.
كما أنهم يحبون الرياضة، وكان يوجد في القرية نادي رياضي.
They also love sports, and there was a sports club in the
village.
إضافة إلى فرقة زوزان للرقص والغناء الشعبي الكردي.
In addition to the Zozan troupe for Kurdish folk dance and
singing.
كفر دلة فوقاني من أقدم القرى الموجودة غرب مدينة عفرين.
Kafr Dalleh Fawqani is one of the oldest villages located
west of Afrin.
ربما يزيد عمرها عن أكثر من 500 عام.
Its age might exceed more than 500 years.
حيث توجد فيها مغاور وكهوف قديمة سكنها الإنسان الأول الذي
استوطن في هذه المنطقة.
Where there are old caves and caverns inhabited by the first
humans who settled in this area.
للحديث عن تاريخ كفر دلة فوقاني.
To talk about the history of Kafr Dalleh Fawqani.
يسرنا أن يكون ضيفنا معنا العم محمد كنجو، أبو دلو، مختار
القرية.
We are pleased to have with us Uncle Muhammad Kanjo, Abu
Dilo, the Mukhtar of the village.
يعطيك العافية عمي أبو دلو.
May God give you health, Uncle Abu Dilo.
أهلاً وسهلاً بجيتكم، على راسي، أهلاً وسهلاً.
Welcome, you have honored us, welcome.
الله يكرمك. خلينا نمشي شوي. هلا نحن وين واقفين؟ هاد البيت شو
هاد البيت؟
May God bless you. Let's walk a little. Where are we
standing now? What is this house?
هاد بيت قديم جداً جداً، وما بقي من، متل قلعة يعني.
This is a very, very old house, and what's left of it, like
a castle I mean.
ضل هيك شوي من بيت جدي، بيت جدي مراد.
Just a little bit is left of my grandfather's house, my
grandfather Murad's house.
شقد عمره يعني هالبيت؟
How old is this house exactly?
هالبيت من، طبعاً من بعد الكهوف. الأولين كانوا يبركوا
بالكهوف.
This house is from, of course after the caves. The first
people used to stay in the caves.
ومن بعد الكهوف، إيه عمروه. نعم. يعني هذا أكتر من 500 سنة.
And after the caves, yeah they built it. Yes. I mean this is
more than 500 years old.
500 سنة. طيب احكي لي عن تاريخ الضيعة، من إيمتى بتبدأ
حكايتها؟
500 years. Okay, tell me about the history of the village,
when does its story begin?
شقد عمرها؟ مين سكانها؟ مين أهلها؟
How old is it? Who are its inhabitants? Who are its people?
أهلها، إجوا من قبور البيض، من الجزيرة.
Its people, they came from Qubour Al-Bid, from the Jazira
region.
الجزيرة السورية.
The Syrian Jazira.
جزيرة سورية، إجوا من قبور البيض وسكنوا هون.
The Syrian Jazira, they came from Qubour Al-Bid and settled
here.
طبعاً نتيجة قتال بين بعضهم وكذا، إجوا وصلوا لهون وسكنوا.
Of course, as a result of fighting among themselves and
such, they came, arrived here and settled.
الجد الكبير كان عنده تمان ولاد.
The great-grandfather had eight children.
في واحد منهم سكن بالزوق الكبير.
One of them settled in Al-Zouq Al-Kabir.
والتاني سكن بغازي تبة.
And the second settled in Ghazi Tepe.
والتالت في كفر دلة فوقاني، هو جدنا.
And the third in Kafr Dalleh Fawqani, he is our grandfather.
اللي هو؟
Who is?
اللي هو جدنا.
Who is our grandfather.
اللي اسمه؟
Whose name is?
الجد اللي سكن هون، هو قدور.
The grandfather who settled here, is Qaddour.
وحسن...
And Hasan...
هو أبوه؟
Is he his father?
إيه، لا، حسن سكن بتل غازي.
Yeah, no, Hasan settled in Tal Ghazi.
وعمر في زوق الكبير أو الكبيرة.
And Omar in Zouq Al-Kabir or Al-Kabira.
هلا تل غازي بس هي صايرة هيك هي موجودة أمامنا، صايرة شمالي
كفر دلة فوقاني.
Now Tal Ghazi is located just like this, it is right in
front of us, located north of Kafr Dalleh Fawqani.
نعم. طيب، شرف سيدي، نعم.
Yes. Okay, go ahead sir, yes.
فهيدول من الكهوف صاروا يعمروا...
So these people from the caves started building...
سكنوا بالكهوف هون يعني؟
They lived in the caves here, you mean?
أيوة. تاريخ الموجود على حجرة، 1197 ميلادي. ميلادي.
Yes. The date written on a stone is 1197 AD. AD.
ميلادي. طيب لما إجوا لهون، شو كانوا يشتغلوا؟
AD. Okay, when they came here, what did they work in?
أول شي هيدول عندهم مراعي وحيوانات، فهمت علي شلون؟
First of all, they had pastures and animals, you know what I
mean?
وكان معهم دهب يعني. اشتروا أراضي وصاروا ملاكين، لكا صاروا
ملاكين.
And they had gold with them, I mean. They bought lands and
became landowners, of course they became landowners.
من نص عفرين ومغرب، وانت مغرب لحدود تركيا.
From the middle of Afrin going west, and going west towards
the Turkish border.
هيدول للثلاث عائلات.
These belong to the three families.
من تلات أولاده، اللي إجوا من...
From his three children, who came from...
إي، اللي إجوا من الجزيرة.
Yeah, who came from the Jazira.
من قبور البيض.
From Qubour Al-Bid.
إي من قبور البيض، نعم.
Yeah, from Qubour Al-Bid, yes.
تلاتة سكنوا هون ومع الأسف، واحد راح صوب كفر صفرة.
Three settled here and unfortunately, one went towards Kafr
Safra.
وواحد صوب حارم، وتلاتة ضايعين لحد الآن ما معروفين.
And one towards Harem, and three are lost until now, they
are not known.
هالحكي من شقد من 500 سنة عم تقول؟
This story is from how long ago, from 500 years you say?
أكتر، أكتر من 500 سنة.
More, more than 500 years.
إذاً إجوا لهون، عندهم حيواناتهم، أغنام وماعز.
So they came here, they have their animals, sheep and goats.
أيوة.
Yes.
المنطقة كانت مشجرة ولا شو كانت؟
Was the area forested or what was it?
المنطقة كانت تعج بالبعوض وما بعوض وكلها مي.
The area was swarming with mosquitoes and such, and it was
all water.
مستنقعات يعني؟
Swamps you mean?
إي مستنقعات وأشجار سنديان وما سنديان، حراجية يعني.
Yeah swamps and oak trees and stuff, forestry I mean.
إيه. لا في أراضي خصبة؟
Yeah. No, are there fertile lands?
أنا معك، لكن...
I agree with you, but...
كانت مشجرة بالزيتون؟ لسه؟
Was it planted with olive trees? Not yet?
لا في، في زيتون، في زيتون قديم بس كانت قليل.
No, there is, there are olives, there are old olives but it
was little.
أشجار زيتون قليل، بعدين زرعوه، فتحوه، وزرعوه.
Olive trees were little, then they planted it, cleared it,
and planted it.
اشتغلوا وعمروا هالبيوت اللي عم نشوفهم هلا.
They worked and built these houses that we are seeing now.
تمام. عدد لي العوائل اللي هون.
Alright. List the families here for me.
عوائل هنن أربع عائلات.
The families, they are four families.
عائلة قدور، وإجوا بعد منها سكنوا في كهف هنيك، شعار.
The Qaddour family, and those who came after them and
settled in a cave over there, Sha'ar.
كهف شعار، وفي عائلة اسمها علي.
Sha'ar's cave, and there is a family named Ali.
المهم إجوا من ضيع يعني بعيدة، كمان سكنوا وصاروا عائلة كبيرة،
وعائلة تكه.
Anyway they came from faraway villages, they also settled
and became a big family, and the Takka family.
إجوا من... هلا شعار وعلي عرب؟
They came from... Now Sha'ar and Ali, are they Arabs?
جيس، هنن جيس.
Jeis, they are Jeis.
وعلي حضر، حضر.
And Ali is Hadar, Hadar.
طيب، شلون كانوا عايشين هالناس هون؟ كيف كانت طبيعتهم؟
عاداتهم؟
Okay, how were these people living here? What was their
nature like? Their customs?
والله عايشين ولحد الآن ما بتعرف هذا كردي، هذا عربي أبداً.
By God, they are living, and until now you wouldn't know
this is a Kurd, this is an Arab, never.
ما في فرق، بس إنسان إنسان يعني. كلياتنا من آدم وحواء.
There is no difference, just human being, human being I
mean. We are all from Adam and Eve.
المغارات لسه مستعملينهم؟
Are the caves still being used?
أوف، لسه. أكثر من 15، 20 مغارة لسه.
Oh, still. More than 15, 20 caves still.
بتشوف كل بيت في، قبل ما يتعمر البيت كان في مغارة.
You see every house has, before the house was built, there
was a cave.
يا سلام. وين، وين ساكنين؟
Wow. Where, where are they living?
إيه إيه للآن لكا.
Yeah, yeah, until now of course.
هلا هاد البيت اللي ورانا عمي أبو دلو، هاد شقد عمره هاد؟
الباب قديم.
Now this house behind us, Uncle Abu Dilo, how old is this?
The door is old.
والله أنا وصغير كان هالباب موجود. وعمري 70 سنة.
I swear, since I was little this door was here. And I'm 70
years old.
ما شاء الله، العمر كله.
Mashallah, a long life to you.
يعني من شي 100 سنة، 150 سنة.
I mean it's from around 100 years, 150 years ago.
100، 150 سنة. هلا اللي فهمته إنه أهل كفر دلة بيحبوا
الموسيقا؟
100, 150 years. Now what I understood is that the people of
Kafr Dalleh love music?
طبعاً.
Of course.
بس شو العلاقة بين الموسيقا وبينهم؟ هات لنشوف.
But what is the relationship between music and them? Let's
see.
والله هاد، بدم، بدم الواحد يعني، بدم الكردي بيحب الموسيقا.
Well this is in the blood, in someone's blood I mean, in the
blood of a Kurd he loves music.
كان في فرقة هون؟
Was there a band here?
إيه، أنا كنت منتسب للفرقة، فرقة زوزان للفلكلور الشعبي
الكردي.
Yeah, I was affiliated with the band, the Zozan troupe for
Kurdish popular folklore.
سكنا بحلب طبعاً، والفرقة كانت هنيك بحلب.
We lived in Aleppo of course, and the band was down there in
Aleppo.
وبتعرف هالحرب وكذا، نتيجة حروب كل واحد صار بديرة وصار ببلد.
And you know this war and such, as a result of wars everyone
ended up in a different region and ended up in a different
country.
بس لسه الناس تحب الموسيقا، والموسيقا بدمها؟
But people still love music, and music is in their blood?
لكا، لسه، لسه والله، هلا الولد الصغير بيحب الموسيقا.
Of course, still, still I swear, now a little kid loves
music.
الله يقويكم.
May God give you strength.
هلا ابن ابني عم يقول بتجيبوا لي ما بعرف ايش، زرناي.
Now my grandson is saying you should bring me I don't know
what, a zurna.
خلينا ندخل على هاد البيت. تفضل. حسب ما فهمت إنه هاد بيت
قديم.
Let's enter this house. Go ahead. From what I understood,
this is an old house.
هاد قديم وبيت عمي، يعني عمي بكر.
This is old and it's my uncle's house, I mean my uncle Bakr.
عمك بكر.
Your uncle Bakr.
بيت عمي بكر. طيب تفضل عمي.
My uncle Bakr's house. Okay, please come in, uncle.
يا رب.
Oh God.
السلام عليكم. هون...
Peace be upon you. Here...
وين عمي أبو بكر؟
Where is my uncle Abu Bakr?
أهلاً وسهلاً.
Welcome.
أستاذ شلونك؟
Sir, how are you?
أهلاً وسهلاً.
Welcome.
عمي أبو دلو عم يقول هاد البيت من أقدم البيوت هون بالضيعة.
Uncle Abu Dilo is saying this house is one of the oldest
houses here in the village.
يا سيدي مضبوط البيت يعني على أيام أجدادي.
Sir, it's correct, the house is from the days of my
ancestors.
هنن كانوا يعمروا. بدك تقول مثلاً محل هيك أربع غرف.
They used to build. You could say, for example, a place like
this with four rooms.
بس أربع غرف متل كان كلها...
But four rooms, it was all like...
...yanî hek bi ba'd mitil, kanu ya'milu mitil qenterme.
...meaning if they were together like, they used to build
them like an arch.
Ewe.
Yes.
Ê nehne û beyt 'emmî, qumna qasemna.
So me and my uncle's family, we went and divided it.
Yanî hal beytîn kanu beyt wahid.
I mean, these two houses were one house.
Ewe, a ntu qasemtu bin-nus.
Yes, ah you divided it from the middle.
Qasemna bin-nus.
We divided it in half.
Min eyyam el-ajdad, kan beyt wahid.
Yes.
From the days of the ancestors, it was one house.
Fercîna hek melamihu bes min barra.
Can you show us its features just from the outside.
Selamun aleykum.
Peace be upon you.
Ahlan, ahlan.
Welcome, welcome.
Hallaq haz cib haz?
Is this a well?
Haz cib.
This is a well.
Qadîm?
Is it old?
Haz cib qadîm. Nehne kaman hek şway hek iştexelna fîha,
hateyna fîha hal hajar es-suwan...
This well is old. We also kind of worked on it a little, we
placed these granite stones on it...
Zexrafna aleyha...
We decorated it...
Ê tehandesna aleyha bi hal xaşab w ma xaşab...
Yes, we engineered it with this wood and such...
Haza mceddedînu mu hek?
You renewed it, isn't that right?
Mceddedînu hek min inna.
We renewed it like this from our side.
A qasdek el-beyt kullu mcedded.
Ah, you mean the whole house is renewed.
El-beyt...
The house...
Li'ennu şifit mehtut hon tarîxu...
Because I saw its history put here...
Tarîxu hon... biddak tqul alef û miteyn û sitte û işrîn
hijrî.
Its history here... you could say 1226 Hijri.
Teqrîben miteyn û şway, miteyn sine û şway.
Approximately two hundred and something, two hundred years
and something.
Eywe, 200 sine û şway.
Yes, 200 years and something.
Haz el-asad şu haz?
What is this lion here?
El- ased? A ased.
The... which lion? Ah, the lion.
Ê mazbut mazbut, yanî biddak tqul şixil biddak tqul...
Yes, that's right, I mean you could say it's a work...
Turasîye.
It's heritage.
Hallaq el-beyt kullu ilu eqwas mu hek?
Now the whole house has arches, right?
Yanî eş-şebabîk wel byut wel bwab eqwas.
I mean the windows, the rooms, and the doors are arches.
Ê kan min ewwelu bi şekil qaws.
Yes, it was in the shape of an arch from the beginning.
Nehne meselen zexrafna aleyha meselen min naw' hek jidîd
keza.
We, for example, decorated it with a new style like this.
Jidîd lakin min nefs er-ruh.
It's new but from the same spirit.
Min nefs er-ruh, bes el-beyt mitil ma qult beytî û beyt
'emmî biddak tqul kan beyt wahid.
From the same spirit, but the house, like I said, my house
and my uncle's house used to be one house.
Şu naw' hal hajar? Haz eş-şixil şu bisemmu haz? Xemîs şu
bisemmu haz?
What is the type of this stone? What do they call this work?
What do they call this coating?
Hal hajar nehne jibnah min çol, min el-wudyan, min keza...
We brought this stone from the wild, from the valleys, and
places like that...
Û el-hajarat meselen illi bt'ijibna... illi biddna nt'handes
fîha...
And the stones, for example, that we liked... that we could
engineer on...
Jibnaha w iştexelna fîha. Hiye ka-zexrefe.
We brought them and worked on them. It is like decoration.
Meselen hallaq haş-şejeret en-nexîl... biddak tqul haz mitil
anqûd şu ismu, nexîl.
For example, this palm tree... you could say it's like a
bunch of dates.
Ka'innu şayif ana fî heda am yiştixil bis-simaq w ma simaq w
keza?
It seemed to me like someone is working with sumac and
things like that?
Ê mazbut hallaq el-yom biddak tqul mawsimu.
Yes, that's right, today you could say it's its season.
Ê ehl el-qarye biddak tqul am yiştixlu fîha am bihawşu am
bikeza...
The people of the village are working on it, harvesting it
and such...
Minnu am yistirziqu w minnu am bifîdu el-alem.
They make a living from it and benefit the people with it.
Tayyib xallîna nşûf ustad... Ustad Mihemed yihkîna şway.
Alright, let's go see Teacher Muhammad, let him talk to us a
little.
Şerref.
Welcome.
Ahlan w sahlan. Ahlan w sahlan.
Welcome, welcome.
Şerref.
Welcome.
Hallaq haz simmaq kaman mu hek?
Now this is also sumac, right?
Ê hay kaman simmaq.
Yes, this is also sumac.
Şu byixtilif haz an hazak?
What makes this different from that one?
Hazak min mbarîh, awwelt mbarîh haşna.
We harvested that one yesterday, the day before yesterday.
Bes iza xalleyta bil kîs, byihmerr ektar.
But if you leave it in the bag, it becomes redder.
Eymata byinhhaş haz? Bi ayy şahar?
When is it harvested? In which month?
Bi şahar Temmûz.
In the month of July.
15 eş-şahar, 20 eş-şahar...
The 15th of the month, the 20th of the month...
Yanî min ras eş-şahar w tatle' hek.
I mean from the beginning of the month and so on.
Hkilî... yanî es-simmaq bid-day'a w biz-zira'a muhimme yanî
ktîr... nas bt'îş minnu.
Tell me... I mean sumac in the village and in agriculture is
very important... people make a living from it.
Ê mnit'ayyeş minnu...
Yes, we make a living from it...
W binba' meselen, Hims, Heleb, Şam...
And it is sold, for example, in Homs, Aleppo, Damascus...
Bttajru fîha wla bes min erdkon?
Do you trade it or is it just from your land?
Min ardna.
It's from our land.
Bes, ma bttajru?
But you don't trade it?
La, ma mntajir, min ardna hek.
No, we don't trade, it's just from our land.
Şu naw'u haz es-simmaq?
What type of sumac is this?
Hay simmaq adî.
This is regular sumac.
Simmaq adî.
Regular sumac.
Fî enwa' tanye lis-simmaq?
Are there other types of sumac?
Ê fî... bi ta'mu, byitla' er-ras yanî ekbar min hay şway.
Yes there are... by its taste, its head grows a bit bigger
than this.
Ekbar min hay şway.
A bit bigger than this.
Yanî fî enwa' muta'addide...
I mean there are multiple types...
Şerref şway. Hallaq a sîret... tet'îm.
Excuse me a bit. Now regarding... grafting.
Tet'îm...
Grafting...
Tet'îm eş-şejer indkon hon... simi't innu intu maşhûrîn bi
tet'îm eş-şejer.
Grafting trees here with you... I heard that you are famous
for grafting trees.
Ê am nt'amm eş-şejer.
Yes, we graft trees.
Kîf btt'ammu eş-şejer?
How do you graft trees?
Min jemî' enwa' eş-şejer. Meselen hallaq...
From all kinds of trees. For example, now...
Hay burdane Ebû Sirre isma.
This orange is called Navel.
Fîna nşîl el-bur'um min hay...
We can remove the bud from this...
W nt'amma lhazîk eş-şejere...
And we graft it onto that tree...
Hazîk mu Ebû Sirre, hay Yafawî.
That one is not Navel, it's Jaffa.
Mnşîl el-bur'um min hon...
We remove the bud from here...
W mnhatt 'al şejere el-Yafawî bitşîr... Ebû Sirre.
And we put it on the Jaffa tree and it becomes... Navel.
Fîna nşûf hallaq?
Can we see it now?
Şerref.
Yes.
Go ahead.
Ya Allah.
Oh God.
Hallaq hay bur'um hay... mnşîlu.
Now this bud here... we remove it.
El-bur'um ez-zxîr.
The small bud.
Ê. Mnşîlu bihaş-şekil.
Yes. We remove it like this.
Xalas, şilna ha-lbur'um hallaq.
Done, we have removed the bud now.
Tayyib, tfeddel.
Alright, go ahead.
Mnjîb...
We bring it...
Mnt'am al haş-şekil haza... al-qişre hay...
We graft it like this... on this bark...
Mndrub mitil selîb hek.
We cut it like a cross like this.
Ma bita'assar?
Doesn't it get affected?
La ma bi'essir.
No, it doesn't affect it.
Mnişqaha hek...
We open it like this...
W mnjîb şertaton aw şwayet xirqe... mnrbut fîha.
And we bring tape or a piece of cloth to tie it with.
Bihal şekil haz.
In this shape.
Ê hallaq hek.
Yes, like this now.
Ma bîmût haz, bîmût?
It doesn't die, does it?
Haz ba'd 'aşr iyyam, 'işrîn yom byitla'.
This sprouts after 10 days, 20 days.
Ba'dên...
Then...
Bihaş-şekil bes iza itla' bur'um min hon... mnquss min hon.
Like this, but if a bud grows from here... we cut it from
here.
Mnquss min hon. Ba'd ma yitla'...
We cut it from here. After it sprouts...
Ê, ba'd ma yitla' el-bur'um.
Yes, after the bud sprouts.
Tinjah amaliyet et-tet'îm.
The grafting process succeeds.
Ê.
Yes.
Temam.
Exactly.
Qiltilî hazak Ebû Sirre?
Did you tell me that one is Navel?
Ê û hay Yafawî. Hallaq hay rah tsîr Ebû Sirre.
Yes, and this is Jaffa. Now this will become Navel.
Btsîr kulla Ebû Sirre wella bes haz el-fexid?
Will it all become Navel or just this branch?
La iza qassayna min hon... hal xusn haz kullu bsîr Ebû
Sirre.
No, if we cut it from here... this whole branch becomes
Navel.
W haz bibqa Yafawî.
And this remains Jaffa.
Subhanallah.
Glory be to God.
Şu fî naw' tanî min et-tet'îm? Haz ismu tet'îm bil-bur'um
haz?
What other types of grafting are there? Is this called bud
grafting?
Fî tiffah hallaq ana ta'amtu hon.
In apples, right now I grafted one here.
Hallaq hay şejere wahide... ta'amta ala tlet enwa'.
Yes...
Now this is a single tree... I grafted it with three types.
Şu hinni enwa'?
What are the types?
Hay tiffah asfar ismu Golden.
This is a yellow apple called Golden.
Ê.
Yes.
W hay ahmar. Tiffah ahmar.
And this is red. Red apples.
W hazak naw' tanî.
And that is another type.
Yanî eş-şejere min tlet eqsam ta'amton.
So one tree, you grafted it into three sections.
Maşallah.
As God willed.
Ehl ed-day'a maşhûrîn bit-tet'îm?
Are the village people famous for grafting?
Ê maşhûrîn. Am nt'amim şejerat ez-zeytûn wel himdiyat wes-
simmaq w keza.
Yes, they are famous. We graft olive trees, citrus, sumac,
and so on.
Allah ya'tîk el-afiye ustad Mihemed.
May God give you health, Teacher Muhammad.
Allah y'afîk ustad... ala eynî u rasî, Allah ydimkon yareb.
May God give you health too, teacher... You are very
welcome, may God protect you all.
Ya'tîkum el-afiye.
May God give you health.
Allah y'afîk.
May God give you health too.
Suzana w Hêvîn, uxten min Keferdelê Foqanî am yt'allemu
mûzîqa...
Suzana and Hêvîn, two sisters from Upper Keferdela are
learning music...
Û mitilon mitil adad kbîr min el-etfal weş-şebab bi hal
qarye...
And like them, a large number of children and youth in this
village...
Illi am yhawlu yhafzu ala turason û folkloron el-xina'î el-
kurdî bil mantiqa.
Who are trying to preserve their heritage and Kurdish
musical folklore in the region.
Bidna nt'arraf aleyhon û n'arif min weyn axadu haş-şaxef wel
hub lil mûzîqa û şu am yt'allemu.
We will get to know them and find out where they got this
passion and love for music and what they are learning.
Ya'tîkî el-afiye Suzana.
May God give you health Suzana.
Allah y'afîk.
May God give you health too.
Ayy sef intî?
What grade are you in?
Sef xamis biddî injah es-sadis.
Fifth grade, I want to pass to sixth.
Maşallah. Û intî Hêvîn?
As God willed. And you Hêvîn?
Ana sef talit biddî injah ar-rabi'.
I am in third grade, I want to pass to fourth.
Ya selam.
Oh wow.
As'alkon... haz illi azeftû şu ismu ya Suzana?
Let me ask you... this thing you played, what is its name
Suzana?
Xelîl Îbrahîm.
Khalil Ibrahim.
El-maqtu'a isma Xelîl Îbrahîm, wella illi azafa Xelîl
Îbrahîm?
Is the piece's name Khalil Ibrahim, or the one who played it
was Khalil Ibrahim?
Illi azafa Xelîl Îbrahîm.
The one who played it was Khalil Ibrahim.
Şu isma hal maqtu'a?
What is the name of this piece?
Xelîl Îbrahîm.
Khalil Ibrahim.
Min weyn habbeytî el-mûzîqa intî?
Where did you get the love for music?
Min immî û abûy.
From my mother and father.
Şu biştixlu abûkî û immik?
What do your mother and father do?
Abûy doktor daxiliyye, immî anse.
My father is an internal medicine doctor, my mother is a
teacher.
Mîn minnon byu'zuf ya Hêvîn?
Which one of them plays Hêvîn?
Abûy.
My father.
Ala şu byu'zuf?
What does he play on?
Al-buzuq wel gîtar.
On the buzuq and the guitar.
Wel gîtar. Tayyib leyş habbeytî el-buzuq biz-zat min
beynaton?
And the guitar. Okay, why did you like the buzuq
specifically out of them?
Şifit abûy am bduqq... ajabnî û habbeytu.
I saw my father playing... I liked it and loved it.
Habbeytî. Leyş ma habbeytî el-gîtar illi byu'zuf aleyh
abûkî?
You loved it. Why didn't you like the guitar that your
father plays?
Habbeyt aktar şî el-buzuq.
I liked the buzuq the most.
El-buzuq. Qaddeş fî şebab mitilkon û sabaya hek am yt'allemu
hallaq bid-day'a?
The buzuq. How many youth and girls like you are learning
right now in the village?
Fî ustad am y'allimkon?
Is there a teacher teaching you?
Fî ustad.
Yes.
There is a teacher.
Ê, am y'allimna.
Yes, he is teaching us.
Qaddeş kam talib m'akon?
How many students are with you?
Teqrîben aşra.
Approximately ten.
Aşra.
Ten.
Mustawayatkon kwayse?
Are your levels good?
Ê.
Yes.
Qaddeş sarlkon am tet'allemu azif?
How long have you been learning to play?
Ana sef tanî.
I am in the second level.
Ana min sef et-tanî am a'zif lhallaq.
I have been playing since the second level until now.
Û ana min sef et-talit.
And I am in the third grade.
Tayyib, şu rah tsem'ûna hallaq?
Okay, what are you going to let us listen to now?
Rah nsem'ekon...
We will let you listen to...
Rah nsem'ekon, Yarê min tu lo şivanî.
We will let you listen to "Yarê min tu lo şivanî".
Yarê min tu lo şivanî.
"Yarê min tu lo şivanî".
Ya Allah.
Go ahead.
Ya'tîkum el-afiye.
May God give you health.
Allah y'afîk.
May God give you health too.
Yislamu îdeykî.
Bless your hands.
Hal buzuq... haz illi am ta'zifî aleyh haz...
This buzuq... this one you are playing...
Şu naw'u haz?
What type is it?
Buzuq adî.
A regular buzuq.
W nafs el-buzuq taba' Hêvîn?
And is Hêvîn's buzuq the same?
Ê.
Yes.
Şu enwa' el-buzuq bta'rifî intî?
Do you know the types of buzuqs?
La wella.
No, by God.
Tayyib, el-meqam illi baqa azeftîh aleyh...
Alright, the scale you played on...
Meqam adî.
A regular scale.
Meqam adî ismu?
Its name is regular scale?
Ê, a nota.
Yes, on notes.
An-nota?
On notes?
Ê.
Yes.
Intî bta'rifî ta'zifî an-nota intî?
Do you know how to play on notes?
Ê.
Yes.
Û intî kaman?
And you too?
Ê.
Yes.
Hîlu ktîr.
Very nice.
Hal libis elli labstîh şu ismu haz?
This dress you are wearing, what is its name?
Xeftan.
Kaftan.
Xeftan, haz...
Kaftan, this...
Fîstan kurdî.
Kurdish dress.
Fîstan kurdî, şu eqsamu?
Kurdish dress, what are its parts?
Bes hek... bes yanî haz...
Just like this... just this I mean...
Hay mitil abaye, tneyn yanî?
This is like a cloak, so two pieces?
Ê, tneyn yanî.
Yes, two pieces.
Fîstan û şalwar.
And you?
Dress and trousers.
شروال، كمان هدا كم قسم صدرية وشروال وقميص.
Sirwal, also this is a few parts, a vest, a sirwal, and a
shirt.
إيه.
Yes.
طيب نشوفك شو في المستقبل؟
Ok, what will we see you as in the future?
أنا صيدلانية.
I will be a pharmacist.
ليش؟
Why?
بحب.
I like it.
يا سلام، ما رح تتخصصي في الموسيقى؟
Oh wow, won't you specialize in music?
لا، كمان بدق.
No, I also play (instruments).
بتدقي، رح تتخصصي قصدي في الموسيقى؟
You play. Will you specialize in music, I mean?
لا.
No.
إنت؟
You?
مهندس شو؟
I am an engineer.
What kind of engineer?
معماري.
Architectural.
معماري ليش؟
Architectural, why?
بحبها.
I like it.
طيب شو بتحب، أي نوع من أنواع العمارة اللي بتعتبرك معماري
إنت، شو العمارة اللي بتحبها؟
Ok what do you like, what type of architecture do you
consider as an architect, what architecture do you like?
معمار.
Architecture.
طيب، بدكم تسمعونا هلق موسيقى، آخر شي موسيقى فلكلورية، من
المنطقة هون.
Ok, you will play some music for us now, lastly some
folkloric music, from the region here.
لشي فنان إنتو بتحبوه، لشي رقصة، دبكة، كذا، شو رح تسمعونا
هلق؟
By an artist you like, for a dance, dabke, or something,
what will you play for us now?
رقصة ستي.
My grandmother's dance.
رقصة ستي، بس بدنا نطرب ها.
My grandmother's dance, but we want to be enchanted,
alright.
الله يعطيكم العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يعافيك.
May God grant you health too.
شكرا إلكن، شكرا يا سوزانا وشكرا يا هيفان.
Thank you, thank you Suzana and thank you Hivan.
النزوح والتهجير القسري مثل ما فرض على الناس إنها تنتقل من
مكان إلى مكان ومن بيئة لبيئة،
Displacement and forced migration, just as it forced people
to move from place to place and from environment to
environment,
فرض عليها تنقل أيضا تراثها وفلكلورها الغنائي معها.
it forced them to move their heritage and musical folklore
with them too.
العم أبو حسين مهجر قسرا من مدينة سراقب بريف إدلب.
Uncle Abu Hussein was forcibly displaced from the city of
Saraqib in the countryside of Idlib.
اليوم نحنا على موعد معه لحتى يعزفلنا على الربابة، الآلة
الشعبية بسراقب،
Today we have an appointment with him so he can play the
rababa for us, the traditional instrument in Saraqib,
ولحتى يعتبلنا العتابة الشعبية اللي طالعة من قلبه ومن جوا
بهالظرف الصعب.
and to sing for us the traditional ataba that comes from his
heart and from inside in this difficult situation.
تابعونا لنتعرف على أبو حسين، ونتعرف أيضا على غناءه وفلكلوره
وربابته.
Follow us to get to know Abu Hussein, and to also get to
know his singing, folklore, and rababa.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام.
And upon you be peace.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
يا هلا، يا هلا، يا هلا وسهلا.
Welcome, welcome, welcome.
عمي أبو حسين شلونك؟
Uncle Abu Hussein, how are you?
يا أهلين وسهلين يا هلا، الحمد لله، شلونكم إنتو؟
Welcome, welcome, praise be to God. How are you?
مشتاقين لك.
We missed you.
أهلا وسهلا فيكم.
Welcome to you.
اللون تبعك حلو كتير، وفي من جوا واضح في معاناة، وفي جروح
جوانية.
Your style is very beautiful, and it's clear from inside
there is suffering, and there are internal wounds.
طبعا أكيد يعني معاناة، نحنا معاناتنا مو من 2011 بس، معاناتنا
من سنة السبعين.
Of course, definitely suffering. Our suffering is not just
from 2011, our suffering is from the year seventy.
صحيح. هلق بدي أتعرف عليك قبل كل شي.
True. Now I want to get to know you first of all.
أنا عبد اللطيف العبيد من مدينة سراقب.
I am Abdul Latif Al-Obaid from the city of Saraqib.
أهلا وسهلا فيك، شو كنت تشتغل؟
Welcome. What did you use to work as?
والله أنا كنت قصاب وبشتغل قصاب ومطعم،
Well, I was a butcher and worked as a butcher and in a
restaurant,
وبعدين أنا بالفترة الأخيرة يعني تركت الشغل، ولادي هني كانوا
عم يشتغلوا بمحلات القصبة.
and then recently I left the job, my children were working
in the butcher shops.
طيب هلق هيدي الربابة إنت صنعتها من مفردات محلية هون؟
Ok, now this rababa, did you make it from local materials
here?
إيه طبعا، هون أنا هي عبارة عن تنكة زيت وعصاية مساحة، وعود من
شجرة الرمان،
Yes of course, here it is just an oil tin and a mop stick,
and a stick from a pomegranate tree,
وشريط من دبرياج الموتور، خلال نص ساعة بتكون جاهزة الربابة.
and a wire from a motorcycle clutch. In half an hour, the
rababa is ready.
هلق أنا اللي فهمته إنه إنت يعني حافظان المقامات.
Now, what I understood is that you have memorized the
maqams.
إيه ممارسة، أنا كنت أنا سميع بالأساس، أنا سميع.
Yes, practice. I was a good listener basically, I'm a good
listener.
بسمع لمحمد عبد الوهاب، بسمع لصالح عبد الحي، بسمع لماري
جبران، بسمع لأم كلثوم، الأغاني القديمة،
I listen to Mohamed Abdel Wahab, I listen to Saleh Abdel
Hai, I listen to Marie Jubran, I listen to Umm Kulthum, the
old songs,
من أغاني الثلاثينات، وكل أغنية بعرفها بدقة، بأي مقام، وبأي
كل ما انتقل المطرب من مقام لمقام أنا بتابعه وبعرفه.
from the songs of the thirties. And every song I know
exactly in which maqam, and every time the singer
transitions from one maqam to another, I follow him and know
it.
تمام. معنا هلق بدك تسمعنا اللون المحلي، اللون السراقبي اللي
جبته معك لهون لكفر دلة فوقاني.
Great. Meaning now you want to play for us the local style,
the Saraqib style that you brought with you here to Kafr
Dalla Fawqani.
لنشوف كيف تأثرت كمان هون يعني بهاد الهوى العليل وهاد الصنوبر
والسرو،
Let's see how you were affected here too by this gentle
breeze, these pines and cypresses,
والبيئة الحلوة الجبلية، جيت من منطقة شبيهة يعني شوي زراعية
أو أقرب إلى الصحراء شوي،
and the beautiful mountainous environment. You came from a
similar area, somewhat agricultural or slightly closer to
the desert,
إلى منطقة جبلية ومشجرة، وفيها خضار. كيف تأثرت؟ سمعنا.
to a mountainous and wooded area with greenery. How were you
affected? Let us hear.
نعم والله حقيقة أنا بدي قلك يعني أنا بالبداية كنت كتير تعبان
نفسيا،
Yes, well truthfully I want to tell you, in the beginning I
was very tired psychologically,
لكن بمواجهة ومقابلة هالناس الطيبين بهالقرية بالذات،
but facing and meeting these good people in this village in
particular,
يعني نسوني كل همومي، وخلوني كتير إني أكون مبسوط وسعيد، لأنه
من أطيب ناس وأروع ناس،
they made me forget all my worries, and made me very happy
and glad, because they are among the best and most wonderful
people,
وكنا نتمنى نكون نعرفهم بغير هيك ظروف.
and we wished we could have known them under different
circumstances.
إن شاء الله السوريين كلهم أخوة. تفضل.
God willing, all Syrians are brothers. Go ahead.
يا يابا أحبابي ما مللتوني تملكون.
Oh father, my loved ones, you didn't bore me, you own (me).
وقلبي اللي انضنى بيكم تملكون.
And my heart that has been exhausted by you, you own it.
ولعقب غيبتكم عني يا خلاني، تملكون.
And after your absence from me, my friends, you own.
معتم ما بزغ بيها الضيا.
It has become dark, no light shines in it.
يا عمري ما نمت ليلي بلاهم.
Oh my life, I have not slept a night without them.
ويا عمري ما نمت ليلي بلاهم.
And oh my life, I have not slept a night without them.
أحبابي كتر عليي بلاهم.
My loved ones, their affliction upon me has increased.
يا يابا أخ يا يابا.
Oh father, oh, oh father.
من أي مقام هيدي عمي أبو حسين؟
From which maqam is this, Uncle Abu Hussein?
مقام الصبا.
The Saba maqam.
مقام الصبا. طيب خلينا نسمع باعتبار وقتنا شوي قصير، خلينا
نسمع شي من وحي الرحلة من سراقب لهون.
The Saba maqam. Ok, let's hear, since our time is a bit
short, let's hear something inspired by the journey from
Saraqib to here.
وحي التهجير والنزوح القسري، بغير مقام.
The inspiration of forced displacement and migration, in a
different maqam.
يا يابا وأنا لأبكي على حالي وأنوحاي.
Oh father, and I will cry over my state and wail.
وبعيني حليت الدنيا وأنا حيا.
And the world became sweet in my eyes while I am alive.
يا يابا ولا أبكي على حالي وأنوحاي.
Oh father, and I will cry over my state and wail.
وبعيني حليت الدنيا وأنا حيا.
And the world became sweet in my eyes while I am alive.
وصديق الما يودني بالدنيا.
And the friend who does not love me in this world,
وأنا حي وشو أعمل بيه حدر ذرات التراب؟
while I am alive, what would I do with him under the grains
of dust?
يا يابا يا يابا.
Oh father, oh father.
الله يعطيك العافية عمي أبو حسين.
May God give you health, Uncle Abu Hussein.
الله يعافيك.
May God give you health too.
شكرا إلك، وإن شاء الله هيك الله بيفرح قلبكم برجوع قريب بإذن
الله لمناطقكم.
Thank you, and God willing, may God gladden your hearts with
a near return, God willing, to your areas.
إن شاء الله، بوجودكم يا رب، الله يسلمنا إياكم.
God willing, with your presence, oh Lord. May God keep you
safe for us.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
شرفت أستاذ، على راسي.
You honored us Mr., on my head.
شلونك؟
How are you?
بارك الله فيك، شرفت أستاذ مصطفى.
God bless you, you honored us Mr. Mustafa.
الله يكرمك، نتعرف عليك؟
May God honor you, can we get to know you?
عبد المعين كنجو إداري نادي كفر دلة.
Abdul Moin Kanjo, administrator of the Kafr Dalla club.
الله يعطيك العافية، إيش عم تساووا هون؟
May God give you health, what are you doing here?
والله هادا ملعب ضيعتنا، طبعا مو مخدم زيادة،
Well this is our village's stadium. Of course it is not
well-serviced,
تأسس النادي بـ 2019، هلق تحولنا لعفرين، على ملعب كبير عم
ندرب.
the club was founded in 2019. Now we moved to Afrin, we are
training on a large field.
هون مقر وهنيك وهنيك؟
Is there a headquarters here, and there and there?
إننا مقر هنيك وهنيك، شباب عم يتدربوا...
We have a headquarters there and there, the youth are
training...
أيام التدريب في عنا سيارات، يعني مناخد من هون سيارات على
عفرين مشان الولاد يتدربوا. طبعاً عنا أربع فئات.
During training days we have cars, I mean we take cars from
here to Afrin for the kids to train. Of course, we have four
categories.
قواعد، ناشئين، شباب، رجال.
Four.
Youth, juniors, teens, and men.
ما شاء الله.
Masha'Allah.
الحمد لله، وفي عنا كمان سلة، عم نشتغل عليها، وفي عنا كمان
لاعبين طاولة.
Thank God, and we also have basketball that we are working
on, and we also have table tennis players.
طاولة؟
Table tennis?
كمان.
Yes.
Also.
حلو، قديش عدد المنتسبين للنادي؟
Yes.
Beautiful, how many members are in the club?
والله تقريباً بدك تقول يعني، تقريباً المعتمدين اللي
بيعتمدوا، إيوا معتمدين تقريباً شي خمسة وسبعين لاعب.
Well, you could say approximately, the reliable ones who are
depended on, yes, reliable ones are about 75 players.
ممتاز. كلهم من الضيعة؟
Excellent. Are they all from the village?
أغلبيتهم من الضيعة، في عنا طبعاً كفر دلة، نادي كفر دلة متكون
من كفر دلة فوق وتحت يعني.
Most of them are from the village. Of course, the Kafar
Dilli club consists of Upper and Lower Kafar Dilli.
الفوقاني والتحتاني.
Upper and Lower.
إيوا.
Yes.
يعني ضيعتين.
So two villages.
إيوا ضيعتين، وطبعاً في عنا لاعبين جداد كمان منتسبين غير
الضيعة، بيلعبوا معنا كمان.
Yes, two villages, and of course we also have new players
who joined from outside the village, they play with us too.
لاعبين جداد كمان؟ من وين؟
New players too? From where?
في عنا لاعبين فئة بتيجينا من إدلب، في عنا لاعبين بيجوا من
إعزاز، من دارة عزة، هدول منتسبين معنا.
We have a group of players coming from Idlib, we have
players coming from A'zaz, from Darat Izza. These are
affiliated with us.
مهجرين أو مو مهجرين، من حقهم يلعبوا.
Displaced or not, it's their right to play.
إيوا، إيوا، إيوا.
Yes, yes, yes.
إيش ترتيبكم أنتو كنادي؟
What is your ranking as a club?
والله الحمد لله عم نلعب هلق بدرجة أولى. أول شي شفنا كتير
صعوبة، ما كان هال يعني الخبرة...
Well, thank God we are currently playing in the first
division. At first we faced a lot of difficulty, there
wasn't much experience...
...إي بالتمارين، بكيفية التعامل مع الملعب الكبير العشبي، غير
هاد.
...with training, with how to deal with the large grass
pitch, unlike this one.
هداك منظم أكتر، بدو يعني سيستم احترافي.
That one is more organized, it requires a professional
system.
لبين ما شبابنا أخدوا وجه على الملعب الكبير، وطبعاً هاد ملعب
صغير، هداك ملعب كبير ما بدك اللاعب ما خرجو يركض ويرجع يعني
بدو مسافة.
Until our youth got used to the big pitch. And of course,
this is a small pitch, that is a large pitch, you need the
player to be able to run and return, it requires distance.
يعني أنتو درجة أولى على مستوى المناطق المحررة أو...
So you are first division at the level of the liberated
areas or...
هلق عم نلعب، إي عم نلعب على درجة أولى هلق.
The liberated areas, yes.
Now we are playing, yes we are playing in the first division
now.
أخدتوا شي بطولة؟
Did you win any championship?
هديك السنة طلعنا التاني على المحرر كلو.
Last year we came second in all the liberated areas.
ما شاء الله.
Masha'Allah.
الله يعطيكن العافية.
Thank God.
May God give you health.
إيوا بدنا دعمك يا أستاذ مصطفى.
Yes, we need your support, Mr. Mustafa.
إي دعمك هلق هي الكاميرا عم بتصور.
Your support is here, the camera is filming right now.
على راسي، على راسي.
On my head, on my head.
بارك الله فيك، أهلاً وسهلاً.
God bless you, welcome.
شرفتنا أستاذ.
You honored us, sir.
الله يوفقكم يا رب.
May God grant you success.
على راسي.
On my head.
(Music playing)
السلام عليكم. شلونك؟ يا شباب. عصرية، أهلاً وسهلاً.
Peace be upon you. How are you? Guys. Good afternoon,
welcome.
أهلاً وسهلاً بعمي. حياك الله أستاذ. يا هلا بك.
Welcome uncle. May God greet you sir. Welcome to you.
يا هلا، عمو شلونك؟
Welcome, uncle, how are you?
الحمد لله سالمين، كيفك؟
Thank God we are safe, how are you?
خليني أقعد بالنص. ارتاح، ارتاح، ارتاح.
Let me sit in the middle. Rest, rest, rest.
العصرية، وباركين هون، مبسوطين ومرتاحين. شلونك عمو؟
It's the afternoon, and you're sitting here, happy and
relaxed. How are you uncle?
والله الحمد لله كيفك؟
Well thank God, how are you?
الحمد لله، شلون الوضع هون، احكيلي؟ أوضاع الناس، كيف عايشين؟
Thank God, how is the situation here, tell me? The people's
situation, how are they living?
الحمد لله كويس.
Thank God it's good.
شلون يعني قلي شلون كويس؟
How, I mean, tell me how is it good?
يعني بإيدنا شوية ضعيف يا أستاذ، نحنا منخجل...
I mean it's a bit weak in our hands, sir, we are shy...
احكي كردي، شو بدك احكي.
Speak Kurmanji, speak whatever you want.
Rind e, tiştekî wisa nîne, tiştên me temam e, tiştekî me
nîne, elhemdulillah rind e, temam e, rihet in...
It is good, there is nothing as such, our things are fine,
we have no problems, thank God it is good, fine, we are
comfortable...
Tiştek nîne yanî rewş rind e. Hemû tişt wisa ye.
Elhemdulillah.
There's nothing, meaning the situation is good. Everything
is like that. Thank God.
شو عم بيقول؟
What is he saying?
عم بيقول الوضع كويس يعني الحمد لله ضيعتنا كويسة، ما صار شي
فيها، و...
He is saying the situation is good, I mean thank God our
village is good, nothing happened to it, and...
عرب وأكراد عايشين مع بعض يعني متل الأخوة، وكليتنا الحمد لله
عم نعيش مع بعض.
Arabs and Kurds live together like brothers, and we are all
living together, thank God.
كويس، الحمد لله. احكي لي، احكي لي هون عن العادات والتقاليد.
عادات الناس...
Good, thank God. Tell me, tell me about the customs and
traditions here. The customs of the people...
أنا بعرف إنو نسبة التعليم عندكم هون كتير مرتفعة قبل شي.
I know that the education rate here is very high,
beforehand.
والله عادات وتقاليد يعني... في ناس عم يروحوا عالزراعة، في
ناس يعني عن... في ناس عم يدرسوا، يعني مشكل من الأول.
Well, customs and traditions, I mean... There are people who
go to agriculture, there are people, I mean... There are
people studying, I mean it's been mixed since the beginning.
أكتر شي عم يعتمدوا عالدراسة.
They rely mostly on studying.
في متعلمين كتير، شهادات كتير؟
Are there many educated people, many degrees?
في يمكن حوالي تلاتين دكاترة، وعشر صيادلة.
There are maybe around thirty doctors, and ten pharmacists.
وباقي التخصصات؟
And the rest of the specialities?
وباقي التخصصات يمكن في خمسين مهندسين، وفي يعني بكالوريا يمكن
في خمس مية واحد.
And the rest of the specialties, maybe there are fifty
engineers, and there are, I mean high school graduates,
maybe there are five hundred.
ما شاء الله، ما شاء الله، الله يزيد ويبارك.
Masha'allah, masha'allah, may God increase and bless you.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
حضرتك من وين؟
Where are you from?
أنا من معرة النعمان، بلدة تلمنس.
I am from Ma'arrat an-Nu'man, the town of Talmannis.
أهلاً وسهلاً فيك، مهجر لهون.
Welcome, you are displaced here.
احكيلي عن أحوال المهجرين.
Yes, displaced.
Tell me about the conditions of the displaced people.
والله الحمد لله رب العالمين يعني طلعنا من بلدنا بظرف إنت
الفترة الأخيرة عندما نزحت معرة النعمان وسراقب.
Well, thank God, Lord of the worlds, I mean we left our
hometown under the circumstances of the recent period when
Ma'arrat an-Nu'man and Saraqib were displaced.
وصلنا هون عالقرية، يعني والله معتبرين إنا كأنا موجودين
ببلدنا، الحمد لله بالنسبة للشعب.
We arrived here in the village, I mean by God we consider
ourselves as if we are in our own hometown, thank God
regarding the people.
يعني نحنا وإياهم الحمد لله فوراً تأقلمنا وشعب طيب وشعب
مسالم، وشعب كريم كمان، مضياف.
I mean, we and them, thank God, immediately adapted, and
they are kind people, peaceful people, and generous people
too, hospitable.
الحمد لله، فرص العمل هون شلون فرص العمل إلكن؟
Thank God, what about the job opportunities here, how are
the job opportunities for you?
بالنسبة، بالنسبة فرص العمل في القرية هوني قليلة شوي لأنو
هوني ريف، كذا...
Regarding, regarding job opportunities in the village here,
they are a bit scarce because it's the countryside here, you
know...
شو بتشتغلوا؟
What do you work as?
نحنا كمان مجالنا زراعي يعني، يعني عنا أراضي زراعية، زيتون،
كذا...
Our field is also agricultural, I mean, I mean we had
agricultural lands, olives, and so on...
نفس مجال عمل القرية.
The same field of work as the village.
تمام، تمام. عمو تحكيلي عن الخدمات هون شلون؟
Okay, okay. Uncle, tell me about the services here, how are
they?
الحمد لله رب العالمين مليح... بس الشغل هون ضيعة فقيرة ما
عندو شي، شغل قليل...
Thank God, Lord of the worlds, it's good... but work here,
it's a poor village, they have nothing, work is scarce...
والعالم عايشة، بس الحمد لله بس عم قول، بس بالفعل شباب باركين
ما عندن شغل، شغلهم ضعيف.
And people are living, but thank God I am just saying, but
in reality the young men are sitting, they have no work,
their work is weak.
فرص عمل قليلة وفي فقر.
Job opportunities are scarce and there is poverty.
شو والفقر يعني؟
What, and poverty meaning?
فقر، فقر.
Poverty, poverty.
إي فقر ما عم بقلك في فقر.
Yes poverty, aren't I telling you there is poverty.
يعني شغل ما في، شغل ضعيف.
I mean there is no work, work is weak.
الحمد لله رب العالمين، عايشين.
Thank God, Lord of the worlds, we are living.
بدي أسأل الأستاذ هون... الخدمات عندكم بالضيعة هون شلون؟
I want to ask the gentleman here... how are the services in
your village here?
بأي ناحية؟
In what aspect?
يعني متلاً صرف صحي، مياه، خبز، كهربا، مي...
I mean for example sewage, water, bread, electricity,
water...
والله صرف الصحي ما في عنا، مشكلة يعني... هي صرف الصحي ضروري
لازم يتعالج.
By God, there is no sewage for us, it's a problem I mean...
this sewage is necessary, it must be treated.
يعني تلاقي المي نازلة بالشارع أو ريحة يعني وخاصة نحنا الدنيا
بالصيف يعني ما كويس طاول.
I mean you find water flowing in the street or smell I mean,
and especially us, it's summer, I mean it's not good at all.
ناحية الخدمات التانية، المي موجودة في، الحمد لله.
Regarding other services, water is available, there is,
thank God.
بالنسبة للكهربا كل العالم مركبين طاقات شمسية يعني عم
يستفيدوا من هالشي.
Regarding electricity, everyone has installed solar panels,
I mean they are benefiting from this.
الحمد لله.
Thank God.
الحمد لله، الحمد لله، آخر سؤال للأستاذ... إيش اللي تعلمتوه،
أنتو كـ... نازحين من أهل الضيعة؟
Thank God, thank God, last question to the gentleman... What
have you learned, as... displaced people, from the people of
the village?
والله طيبة القلب، يعني... شعب إيش بدي أوصفلك شلون يعني...
شعب طيب، شعب مسالم، بشكل عام يعني هون الشعب الكردي كلو شعب
كويس وشعب مسالم وشعب كريم يعني...
By God, good-heartedness, I mean... people, how can I
describe it to you, I mean... kind people, peaceful people,
in general I mean here the Kurdish people are all good
people, peaceful people, and generous people, I mean...
الحمد لله. الله يعطيكم العافية، شكراً إلكن. انبسطنا كتير
معكم.
Thank God. May God give you health, thank you. We enjoyed
our time with you very much.
حياكم الله.
May God greet you.
أعزائي المشاهدين، انتهت هذه الجولة والتي قدمناها لكم من قرية
كفر دلة فوقاني في ريف مدينة عفرين الغربي. سنكون معكم في
الأسبوع القادم في قرية جديدة وحلقة جديدة من برنامج جولات.
السلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته.
Dear viewers, this tour which we presented to you from the
village of Kafar Dilli Foqani in the western countryside of
Afrin has ended. We will be with you next week in a new
village and a new episode of the Tours program. Peace, mercy
and blessings of God be upon you.
Lê dewê dewê dewê dewê
Oh, buttermilk, buttermilk, buttermilk, buttermilk
Lê şeviyê dewê hoy
Oh, the evening buttermilk, hoy
Lê dewê dewê dewê dewê
Oh, buttermilk, buttermilk, buttermilk, buttermilk
Lê lê şeviyê dewê hoy
Oh, oh, the evening buttermilk, hoy
Hê lê dostê bilbilo ro ava neçû Xwedê bayê
Oh friend nightingale, the sun hasn't set, God brings the
wind
Lê rabe rabe em biçin Keferdelê
Oh get up, get up, let's go to Keferdelê
Lê çarşef li rû da ye
Oh, the chador is covering the face
Lê dostê çarşef li rû da ye
Oh friend, the chador is covering the face
Hê lê dostê bila tu zanibê şev û rojê min di xeyalê te da ye
Oh friend, if only you knew, my night and day are in your
imagination
Ne xwest cîranê min dîtin bi hêsir e lê di Keferdelê da ye
My neighbors didn't want to see me with tears, but it is in
Keferdelê
Lê dîlan e tê da ye
Oh, there is a wedding in it
Lê canê tê da ye
Oh, the soul is in it
(Instrumental music)